Bertram D. Lewin Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Bertram D. Lewis Papers 1883-1974 1927-1970
MSS61949
Lewin, Bertram D. (Bertram David), 1896-1971
10,000 items
20 containers plus 1 oversize
10 linear feet
1 microfilm reel
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Psychoanalyst, educator, and writer. Correspondence, diaries, biographical data, reports, surveys, speeches and writings, school papers, certificates, legal documents, and photographs documenting Lewin's contributions to psychoanalysis in the United States through his writings, teaching, and involvement in various psychoanalytic organizations.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Abraham, Karl, 1877-1925. On character and libido development. 1966.; Aichhorn, August, 1878-1949--Correspondence.; Arlow, Jacob A. Jacob A. Arlow papers.; Bacon, Catherine--Correspondence.; Eissler, K. R. (Kurt Robert), 1908-1999--Correspondence.; Fenichel, Otto--Correspondence.; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965--Correspondence.; Freud family.; Freud, Anna, 1895-1982--Correspondence.; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939--Anniversaries, etc.; Gitelson, Maxwell, 1902-1965--Correspondence.; Hendrick, Ives, 1898-1972--Correspondence.; Jacobson, Edith--Correspondence.; Jones, Ernest, 1879-1958--Correspondence.; Kenworthy, Marion E., (Marion Edwena), 1891-1980--Correspondence.; Kubie, Lawrence S. (Lawrence Schlesinger), 1896-1973. Lawrence S. Kubie papers.; Lewin, Bertram D. (Bertram David), 1896-1971.; Lewin, Bertram D. (Bertram David), 1896-1971. Image and the past. 1968.; Maverick, Maury, 1895-1954--Correspondence.; Menninger, Karl A. (Karl Augustus), 1893-1990--Correspondence.; Meyer, Adolf, 1866-1950--Correspondence.; Meyer, Adolf, 1866-1950.; Nunberg, Herman, 1884-1970--Correspondence.; O'Mara, Jerry. Jerry O'Mara papers.; Sachs, Hanns, 1881-1947--Correspondence.; Schur, Max--Correspondence.; Strachey, James--Correspondence.; Waelder, Robert--Correspondence.; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975--Correspondence.; Wittels, Fritz, 1880-1950--Correspondence.
Organizations
American Psychoanalytic Association.; New York Psychoanalytic Institute.; New York Psychoanalytic Society.; University of Pittsburgh--Faculty.
Subjects
Compulsive behavior.; Dreams.; Elation.; Psychoanalysis--Societies, etc.; Psychoanalysis--Study and teaching--United States.; Psychoanalysis--United States--Societies, etc.; Psychoanalysis.; Psychoanalysts--Europe, Eastern.; Psychology--Study and teaching--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons, German--Psychological testing.
Occupations
Authors.; Educators.; Psychoanalysts.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Bertram David Lewin, psychoanalyst, professor, and writer, were given to the Library of Congress by the Sigmund Freud Archives, Inc., in 1986. A few items were donated separately by Lewin in 1964 and 1974.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Bertram David Lewin are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of Walter C. Langer's Psychological Analysis of Hitler: His Life and Legend is available in these papers for use in the Manuscript Division. The microfilm consists of a negative copy and is not available for purchase and may not be borrowed on interlibrary loan.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1896, Nov. 30 Born, Victoria, Tex.
1916 B.A., University of Texas, Austin, Tex.
1920 M.D., Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md.
1926 1927 Attended Berlin Psychoanalytic Institute, Berlin, Germany
1926 Married Alice Julia Benjamin
1931 Cofounder, New York Psychoanalytic Institute, New York, N.Y.
1932 1971 Cofounder and editor, Psychoanalytic Quarterly
1936 1937 President, New York Psychoanalytic Society, New York, N.Y.
1936 1943 Chairman, Emergency Committee on Relief and Immigration (helping European psychoanalysts escape Axis countries before and during World War II)
1946 1947 President, American Psychoanalytic Association
1950 Published The Psychoanalysis of Elation. New York: W. W. Norton & Co.
1955 1961 Director, Survey of Psychoanalytic Education, American Psychoanalytic Association
1960 Published Psychoanalytic Education in the United States, with Helen Ross. New York: W. W. Norton & Co.
1962 1971 Visiting professor of psychoanalysis, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Pittsburgh, Pa.
1969 Publication of The Image and the Past. New York: W. W. Norton & Co.
1971, Jan. 12 Died, Pipersville, Pa.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Bertram David Lewin (1896-1971) span the years 1883-1974, with the bulk of the material dating from 1927 to 1970. The collection documents Lewin's contributions to psychoanalysis in the United States through his writings, teaching, and involvement in various psychoanalytic organizations. The papers consist of correspondence, diaries, biographical data, reports, surveys, speeches and writings, school papers, certificates, legal documents, and photographs. The collection is organized into five series: Family and School Papers, General Correspondence, Subject File, Writings File, and Oversize.
Lewin was born in 1896 in Victoria, Texas, the son of Samuel Lewin, a German immigrant, and Justine Levy, a Texas native. Following his 1916 graduation from the University of Texas in Austin, Lewin enrolled in Johns Hopkins University Medical School in Baltimore, Maryland, where he studied with psychiatrist Adolf Meyer. Lewin received his medical degree in 1920 and, after completing his residency in Baltimore, worked for several years with Charles B. Dunlap at the New York Psychiatric Institute on Ward's Island. Like many early students of psychoanalysis, Lewin spent several years in Europe attending classes, working on supervised cases, and undergoing analysis. During his time in Europe between 1926 and 1927, Lewin worked first with Paul Schuster in the Friedrich Wilhelm Krankenhaus and later attended the Berlin Psychoanalytic Institute. In 1927 Lewin returned to New York where he established a practice in psychiatry and psychoanalysis.
Upon his return to the United States, Lewin became active in several psychoanalytic institutions. In 1931 Lewin became one of the founders of the New York Psychoanalytic Institute, whose curriculum was closely modeled on that of the Berlin Psychoanalytic Institute. A year later, he established the Psychoanalytic Quarterly with Gregory Zilboorg, Franwood E. Williams, and Dorian Feigenbaum. Lewin remained on the periodical's editorial board until his death in 1971. Lewin served as president of the New York Psychoanalytic Society from 1936 to 1937 and of the American Psychoanalytic Association from 1946 to 1947.
Many of Lewin's writings became standard psychoanalytic texts. His early works focus on compulsive character, the body as phallus, claustrophobia, and hypomania. Later writings deal particularly with the psychology of dreams and elation. Fluent in German and Spanish, Lewin also translated works by Franz Alexander, Karl Abraham, Otto Fenichel, and Angel Garma. In 1955 he accepted the directorship of the American Psychoanalytic Association's survey of psychoanalytic education. Lewin and Helen Ross, the project's associate director, published their findings in Psychoanalytic Education in the United States in 1960. Mixed reaction to the way in which the survey was conducted and to its final report led to Lewin and Ross's resignations in 1961. For the next ten years, until his death in 1971, Lewin taught psychology and psychoanalysis at the University of Pittsburgh.
The Family and School Papers include family correspondence, legal documents, and genealogical information. Among the earliest material is an autograph book kept by Lewin's mother, Justine Levy, between 1883 and 1888, and a set of diaries and photographs recording a trip taken by Lewin and his parents to Europe in 1910. The series also contains student papers, including class notes and other material, from Lewin's undergraduate work at the University of Texas and medical studies at Johns Hopkins University. This latter material includes notes from Adolf Meyer's psychology class. Although little material exists in this series from Lewin's years in Berlin, a letter written in 1926 to Lewin's mother-in-law, Irma Benjamin, contains an account of a visit paid by Lewin and his wife to the Freud family.
The General Correspondence series traces developments in psychoanalytic theory and practice from the mid-1920s to 1970. Correspondence contains lively exchanges with colleagues, including August Aichhorn, Catherine Bacon, K. R. Eissler, Otto Fenichel, Anna Freud, Maxwell Gitelson, Ives Hendrick, Ernest Jones, Edith Jacobson, Marion E. Kenworthy, Karl A. Menninger, Adolf Meyer, Herman Nunberg, Hanns Sachs, Max Schur, James Strachey, Robert Waelder, and Fritz Wittels, among others. Lewin's correspondence also includes letters from Felix Frankfurter concerning efforts to aid European psychoanalysts in Axis countries during the 1930s, a letter from novelist Thornton Wilder discussing The Ides of March, and correspondence with Texas politician Maury Maverick.
The Subject File largely concerns Lewin's involvement in various psychoanalytic organizations. Lewin's directorship of and eventual resignation from the American Psychoanalytic Association survey of psychoanalytic education project is documented by correspondence, minutes, recommendations, and reports. The series also contains files from Lewin's association with the University of Pittsburgh Medical School during the last decade of his life. Other activities covered in the Subject File include efforts to secure Edith Jacobson's release after her arrest by the Gestapo in 1936, Lewin's psychological evaluation of German prisoners of war in 1945, and his chairmanship of the American Psychoanalytic Association's Freud centenary celebrations in 1956. Posthumous files contain writings by Jacob A. Arlow, Lawrence S. Kubie, and Jerry O'Mara on Lewin's life and contributions to psychoanalysis.
The Writings File includes manuscripts, printed copies, and research material from Lewin's articles, lectures, books, reviews, and poetry. Topics covered include Lewin's research on dreams, elation, compulsive behavior, and psychoanalytic education. The series includes a long run of correspondence concerning Lewin's dream screen theories, as well as manuscripts and publishers' correspondence regarding The Image and the Past and Lewin's translation of Karl Abraham's On Character and Libido Development. Writings by various colleagues complete the series.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
Family and School Papers, 1883-1974
General Correspondence, 1924-1973
Subject File, circa 1920-1973
Writings File, 1908-1971
Oversize, 1913-circa 1970
Container List
- Family and School Papers, 1883-1974 (Box 1-4)
  Correspondence and subject files, including diaries, legal documents, genealogical matter, biographical data, photographs, various student papers, school and university memorabilia, and miscellaneous material.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of person within the correspondence file and by name of person, topic, or type of material within the subject file.
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Acker, Jesse, 1964-1965, undated
    - Benjamin, Irma (mother-in-law), 1926
    - Lewin, David (son), 1944
    - Lewin, Wera (cousin), 1932-1969
    - Miscellaneous postcards, 1910-1915
  - Subject file
    - European trip, 1910
      - Diaries, (2 folders)
      - Photographs, (2 folders)
    - Genealogy of Lewin family, 1966, 1971
    - Legal documents
      - Lewin estate, 1971-1974
      - Miscellaneous, 1884-1945
      - San Antonio property, San Antonio, Tex., 1921-1963
    - Lewin, Justine Levy (mother), autograph book, 1883-1888
    - Student papers (Box 2)
      - Johns Hopkins University Medical School, Baltimore, Md., notes
        - Abstracts mainly on "character," circa 1920-1921
        - Miscellaneous, 1918-1919
        - Notebook, 1915-1927
      - San Antonio High School, San Antonio, Tex.
        - Graduation program and diploma, 1913 See also Oversize
        - Yearbooks, 1912-1913, (2 folders)
        - "Woodrow Wilson," short paper, 1910
      - University of Texas, Austin, Tex.
        - Class reunion, 1966
        - Notes
          - Aphasia, 1913
          - English, 1915
          - Psychoanalysis, 1913
          - Zoology, 1914-1916, (2 folders) (Box 3)
        - Yearbooks
          - 1915
          - 1916 (Box 4)
    - United States Army, discharge papers, 1918
- General Correspondence, 1924-1973 (Box 4-7)
  Letters sent and received by Lewin, with attached and related matter.
  Organized alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Aichhorn, August, 1946-1948 (Box 4)
  - Araico, J. Remus, 1950-1964
  - Arlow, Jacob A., 1967-1969
  - Astley, Royden, 1959
  - "A" miscellaneous, 1954-1970
  - Benjamin, John, 1965
  - Bonnett, Sara, 1951
  - Brosin, Henry, 1962-1965
  - "B-D" miscellaneous, 1932-1970, undated, (3 folders)
  - Edelheit, Henry, 1962-1970
  - Eissler, K. R., 1961-1970, undated (Box 5)
  - "E" miscellaneous, 1952-1970
  - Fenichel, Otto and Hanna, 1932-1962, 1952-1970
  - Fischer, Charles, 1965
  - Fountain, Gerard, 1967-1970
  - Frankfurter, Felix, 1936, undated
  - Freud, Anna, 1936-1969
  - Freudenheim, Eika, 1929-1939, undated
  - "F" miscellaneous, 1948-1970
  - Grinberg, Leon, 1962-1968
  - "G" miscellaneous, 1944-1969
  - Hale, Nathan G., Jr., 1959
  - Harnik, Eugen, 1931-1932
  - Hendrick, Ives, 1950-1968
  - Hirsch, Arthur, 1937
  - "H" miscellaneous, 1948-1970, undated
  - Isakower, Otto, 1958-1970
  - Jacobson, Edith, 1955-1967, undated
  - Jones, Ernest, 1932-1955, 1968, undated
  - "J" miscellaneous, 1951-1970
  - Kubie, Lawrence S., 1924-1970, (3 folders)
  - "K" miscellaneous, 1926-1971, undated (Box 6)
  - Levin, Sidney, 1964
  - Lyndon, John, 1965
  - "L" miscellaneous, 1951-1970, undated
  - Maverick, Maury, 1935-1946
  - McCardle, Ellen, 1970, undated
  - Menninger, Karl A., 1960-1968
  - Meyer, Bernard C. ("Buddy"), 1959
  - "M" miscellaneous, 1926-1970
  - Niederland, William G., 1961-1968
  - Nunberg, Herman, 1954-1970, undated
  - O'Mara, Jerry, 1962-1970, undated
  - "O" miscellaneous, 1958-1970, undated
  - Psychoanalytic Quarterly, 1964-1973
  - "P" miscellaneous, 1944-1970
  - Roazen, Paul, 1967-1969
  - "R" miscellaneous, 1953-1970, undated
  - St. John, Robert, 1967-1970
  - Sawyer, Fay, 1966-1968, undated
  - Schur, Max, 1962-1963
  - Sheimo, S. L., 1970
  - Snoek, Andre, 1953
  - Spitz, Rene, 1953-1967
  - Stein, Martin S., 1967-1968
  - Strachey, James, 1940-1955
  - "S" miscellaneous, 1948-1970, undated
  - Tarbox, Raymond, 1967-1969, undated
  - "T" miscellaneous, 1949-1970, undated (Box 7)
  - W. W. Norton & Co., 1948-1954
  - Waelder, Robert, 1954-1966, undated
  - Weiss, Edoardo, 1961
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1955
  - Wittels, Fritz, 1936-1942
  - "W-Z" miscellaneous, 1951-1970
  - Unidentified, 1957-1970, undated
- Subject File, circa 1920-1973 (Box 7-13)
  Correspondence, reports, various papers and legal matter, surveys, lists, research data, photographs, and other material relating to Lewin's personal and professional activities.
  Organized alphabetically by topic or type of material.
  - Birthdays (Box 7)
    - Sixtieth, 1956
    - Seventieth, 1966
  - Boston Psychoanalytic Society, twenty-fifth anniversary, Boston, Mass., 1958
  - Certification papers and miscellaneous documents, 1927-1957
    - See also Oversize
  - Financial, 1921-1949
  - Freud centenary celebrations ( 1956 ), sponsored by the American Psychoanalytic Association
    - Correspondence, 1954-1956
    - Miscellany, 1956, undated (Box 8)
    - Photographs from exhibits
      - Chicago, Ill., American Psychoanalytic Association annual meeting, 27-28 Apr. 1956
      - New York, N.Y., New York Academy of Medicine, 9-19 May 1956, (2 folders)
  - Indexes to personal papers, 1950-1965
  - International Psychoanalytic Congress, Berlin, Germany, 1922
  - Interview with German prisoners of war, 1945
  - Jacobson, Edith, protest about her arrest, 1936
  - Miscellany, 1940-1968, undated
  - New York Psychoanalytic Institute, New York, N.Y., reports and minutes, 1963-1965 (Box 9)
  - New York Psychoanalytic Society, New York, N.Y., 1932
  - Obituaries, 1958-1968, undated
  - Personal library, 1962
  - Photographs and lantern slides, circa 1920-circa 1970 See also Oversize, (3 folders)
  - Pittsburgh Psychoanalytic Institute, Pittsburgh, Pa., schedules, 1966
  - Posthumous files, regarding Lewin, by others (Box 10)
    - Arlow, Jacob A.
      - "The Examined Life," 1971
      - Selected Writings of Bertram D. Lewin (1973)
        - Correspondence with Psychoanalytic Quarterly, 1971-1972
        - Introduction and chapter prefaces, galley proofs, undated
    - Kubie, Lawrence S., information on Lewin for biography, 1971-1973
    - O'Mara, Jerry, tribute to Lewin, 1971
  - Sigmund Freud Archives, Inc., New York, N.Y., 1951-1969
  - Survey of Psychoanalytic Education, American Psychoanalytic Association
    - Acceptance of directorship and responses, 1955
    - Arlow, Jacob A., 1960-1962
    - Boston response, 1958-1959
    - Central fact-gathering committee, 1953-1954
    - Comments on survey memoranda, 1958
    - Fan mail, 1959-1961
    - Final recommendations, 1961-1962
    - Information letters, 1958
    - Kenworthy, Marion E., 1955
    - Meetings, 1956-1957
    - Miscellany, 1956-1959
    - Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute, Philadelphia, Pa., 1958
    - Possibility of continuing as director, 1961
    - Proposal for study of training facilities accredited by the American Psychoanalytic Association, 1954
    - Rangell, Leo, 1960-1962
    - Resignation of Lewin and Helen Ross, 1960-1962, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Survey requests, 1957-1959
    - Survey steering committee, 1955-1958
  - University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pa.
    - Correspondence
      - Astley, Royden, 1962-1968
      - Babcock, Charlotte, 1965-1970
      - Brosin, Henry, 1958-1965
      - Coleman, Donald, 1965-1969
      - Kenworthy, Marion E., 1962
      - Miscellaneous, 1962-1967
    - Papers by others
      - Aruffo, Roy N., "Lactation as a Manifestation of Separation Anxiety," 1965
      - Astley, Royden, "Psychoanalytic Content in Residency Training Programs: Future Developments," 1962
      - Borke, Helen, "Continuity and Change," 1963
      - Brosin, Henry, "Human Aggression in Psychiatric Perspective," 1965 (Box 12)
      - Charny, E. Joseph, and Edward J. Carroll, "General Systems Theory and Psychoanalysis," 1964
      - Kehoe, Michael, "Studies of Depressive Responses," circa 1961
      - Lebeau, W. E., "Variations on a Theme by Freud," 1958
      - Loeb, Felix F., "The Fist," 1965
      - Mallott, I. Floyd, and Otto von Mering, "The Ethnic Parameter of Psychiatric Patients," 1964
      - Mitscherlich, Alexander, "Social Ego and Personal Ego" and "A Defense against Mourning," 1964
      - O'Mara, Jerry, "A Contemporary Fable About the Analytic Couch and Scientific Inquiry," undated
      - Pochapin, Sherman W., "Some Emotional Aspects of Deafness," undated
      - Ross, Helen, "On Learning to Read," 1965
      - St. John, Robert, "Undifferentiated Affect and the Smiling Response in Chronic Schizophrenic Women," undated
      - Schwartz, Len, "Pitch Discrimination," 1965
      - Shoemaker, R. J., "The Phenomenon of Dehumanization," 1965
      - Zabarenko, Lucy, "A Report on Observations of Teaching Small Groups of Physicians" and "Watching Doctors Learn," 1965-1966
    - Miscellany
      - Bibliography on research, 1962-1966
      - Honors, thank-you letters, etc., 1962-1965
      - Lecture transcript on early development of psychoanalysis in the United States, circa 1963
      - Photographs, 1963-1970 (Box 13)
      - Printed matter, 1965, undated
      - Reports
        - Courses taught by Lewin, 1960-1965, (2 folders)
        - Miscellaneous, 1960-1963
      - Schedules, lists, and related material, 1968-1969
- Writings File, 1908-1971 (Box 13-20)
  Manuscripts of articles, books, lectures, speeches, presentations, reviews, and poetry, including drafts, notes, galleys, microfilm, and printed copies, and related correspondence, bibliographic material, and research information.
  First separated into writings by Lewin and writings by others, and then organized by type of material and alphabetically therein by title, topic, or name of author.
  - By Lewin (Box 13)
    - Manuscripts and related materials
      - "Clinical Hints from Dream Studies," 1954
      - "Countertransference in the Technique of Medical Practice," 1946-1949
      - "CURE," notes, 1942-1970
      - Dream screen
        - Correspondence
          - Arlow, Jacob A., 1950-1959
          - Bacon, Catherine G., 1951
          - Bergman, Paul, 1957
          - "B-E" miscellaneous, 1946-1965
          - Fleiss, Robert, 1952-1954
          - "F" miscellaneous, 1954-1958
          - Garma, Angel, 1953
          - Gitelson, Maxwell, 1947-1956
          - Glauber, Peter, 1950-1952
          - Greenberg, Richard, 1963
          - "G" miscellaneous, 1950-1955
          - Hendrick, Ives, 1946
          - "H" miscellaneous, 1950-1960
          - Isakower, Otto, 1948-1961
          - Jones, Ernest, 1955-1956, undated
          - Joseph, Edward, 1958
          - "J" miscellaneous, 1953
          - Kubie, Lawrence S., 1930-1958 (Box 14)
          - "K-L" miscellaneous, 1948-1964
          - Murphy, B. W., 1964
          - "M" miscellaneous, 1947-1954
          - Niederland, William G., 1952-1961
          - "N-R" miscellaneous, 1946-1961
          - Sanz, Perez, 1951-1962
          - "S-Z" miscellaneous, 1946-1965, (2 folders)
        - Miscellany, circa 1950-1960
      - "Dreams and the Use of Regression," 1957-1960
      - "Dreams from Above," quotations collected by Lewin, 1962-1967
      - "Education and the Quest for Omniscience," Alexander Lecture (1957), Institute for Psychoanalysis, Chicago, Ill., 1957-1960
      - "Elation," circa 1950
      - "Fecal Smearing, Menstruation, and the Female Super-Ego," 1930
      - Gudunoff, Boris, notes, undated
      - The Image and the Past
        - Book
          - Correspondence with International Universities Press, 1968-1969
          - Manuscript, 1969 (Box 15)
          - Reviews, thank-you notes, 1966-1970
        - Miscellaneous notes and reference materials, 1966-1968
        - Papers
          - Pittsburgh Psychoanalytic Association (1966), Pittsburgh, Pa., 1966-1967
          - Psychoanalytic Research and Development Fund, Nunberg Lecture (1967), New York, N.Y., 1966-1967
      - "Knowledge and Dreams," read at the Seventh Annual Freud Lectures, Philadelphia Association for Psychoanalysis, Philadelphia, Pa., 4 June 1962
      - "Mankind Discovers Man," with Lawrence S. Kubie, 1951
      - "Nature of Reality, the Meaning of Nothing, with an Addendum on Concentration," 1948, 1968
      - "The Negative Therapeutic Reaction," lecture, undated
      - New York Psychoanalytic Institute and Society, New York, N.Y., lecture, 1946
      - On Character and Libido Development: Six Essays by Karl Abraham ( 1966 )
        - Correspondence with W. W. Norton & Co., 1965-1968
        - Notes and reactions, 1965-1967
      - "Phobias," 1965-1968
      - Poetry
        - Comments and analysis, 1954
        - Composition book, circa 1954 (Box 16)
        - "En Archei," 1954
        - "Gitana in Bucks County and Other Poems," a bound collection, 1954
        - Miscellaneous, published and unpublished, 1954-1960, (3 folders)
        - Reprints of Lewin's poetry, et al., 1954, undated